BAGNELL.
>> REPORTING ON THE MOVES THAT
WE'RE SEEING IN COGECO. I'M
ALSO TRACKING THE MOVES IN
MANULIFE. LET'S TAKE A LOOK AT
THE GRAPH. IT'S TRADING ABOVE
$28 PER SHARE SOMETHING IN A
STRUGGLE TO DO, QUITE FRANKLY,
SINCE 2008 AND PART OF THE
CATALYST IS WHAT IT ANNOUNCED
YESTERDAY, ANNOUNCING
13 BILLION DOLLAR DEAL TO
REASSURE SOME IT'S BOOK IN THE
LONG TERM CARE PART OF ITS
BUSINESS. NOW IN DOING SO,
THEY'RE REWARDING SHAREHOLDERS
WITH A SHARE BUYBACK. IT'S ONE
OF THE REASONS RBC UPGRADED
SHARES OF MANULIFE TODAY.
PUTTING A $34 PRICE TARGET
HERE WE ARE LOOKING AT THE
STOCK TRADING ABOVE 28.
JOINING ME NOW IS ROY GORI,
PRESIDENT AND CEO OF THE
MANULIFE. ROY, THANK YOU SO
MUCH FOR BEING WITH US.
>> GOOD MORNING, AMBER. IT'S
GREAT TO BE WITH YOU. THANK
YOU. TIME LET'S TALK ABOUT
THIS LONG-TERM CARE BUSINESS
AT BECAUSE WE THINK ABOUT USE
SERVE A LIFE INSURER AND AND
REALLY WHAT THE CHALLENGES
WITH LONG-TERM CARE AND WHY IT
WAS CRITICAL TO KIND OF MOVE
IT OFF OF THE MANULIFE BOOKS.
>> WELL, WE DELIGHTED TO
ANNOUNCE YESTERDAY THIS
TRANSACTION, IT IS A MAJOR
MILESTONE IN OUR COMPANY'S
HISTORY, QUITE HONESTLY. AND
ALSO REALLY IS ABOUT
TRANSFORMING IN RESHAPING A
COMPANY TOWARDS LOW RISK AND
HIGH RETURNS. SO WAS A
30 BILLION DOLLAR TRANSACTION
IN TOTAL WITH CLOSE ATLANTIC
AND A BIG PART OF THAT WAS KID
BUSINESS EFFECT 6 BILLION
DOLLARS AND IT MAKES THIS
TRANSACTION THE LARGEST LTC
ALONG TUNCAY TRANSACTION IN
HISTORY. NOW WHAT'S BEING A
DRAG LAST STOP FOR SEVERAL HAS
UNCERTAINTY AROUND LONG TERM
CARE ASSUMPTIONS AS BEING A
DRINK FOR US, BUT HAS BEEN A
DRAG. SO THE ENTIRE INDUSTRY
AND THROUGH THIS TRANSACTION,
WE FEEL THAT WE'VE BEEN ABLE
TO VALIDATE PRUDENCE OF AND
THEN WILL GIVE CONFIDENCE TO
THE MARKET AROUND THE QUALITY
ABOUT GOLD AND THE QUALITY OF
OUR IS A WHICH IS WE YOU KNOW,
A KEY FACTOR IN DRIVING A
REWRITING STAFF. AND AGAIN, WE
THINK THAT THERE'S MUCH MORE
TO BE DONE IN THIS LIQUID
OPTIMISTIC ABOUT THE I THINK
THAT'S THE QUESTION BECAUSE
FOR A LONG TIME FOR INVESTORS,
THEY DIDN'T THINK ANYTHING
COULD BE DONE HERE. AND YOU'RE
ABLE TO DO THIS WITH PART OF
YOUR BOOK.
>> ARE YOU CURRENTLY WORKING
ON ANOTHER DEAL LIKE THIS?
MIGHT IT BE ON SIMILAR TERMS?
>> THAT'S A GREAT QUESTION.
COMPOST TOILETS, THOSE LEE,
THIS IS QUITE A SIGNIFICANT
PERCENTAGE LONG TO CABLE CAN
FACTS 14%, SO IT'S NOT
INSIGNIFICANT, AS I MENTIONED
ARE, IT'S THE LARGEST LTC AND
THE QUESTION IS, WHY AND I
THINK IT'S A COMBINATION
THINGS. THE FIRST IS THAT
WE'VE GOT ENSURING ABOUT AND
WE NOW HAVE MUCH MORE DATE,
THAT HELP SUPPORT THE
ASSUMPTIONS THAT WE'RE USING
TO PREDICT OUR ISN'T HE? AND
JUST A THEY PLAN LEAVE YOU
WITH IS THAT WE'VE SEEN THE
POLL SEEK OUT ON THESE
PORTFOLIO, REDUCED BY 16%
SINCE AND WE NOW HAVE, FACT,
LESS THAN 50 PER SE, ALL
POLICIES THAT WERE ORIGINALLY
SOLD, STILL ON BOOKS. SO THE
FIRST THING IS THAT THE
MATURITY OF PORTFOLIO HAS HAS
DEVELOPED QUITE SIGNIFICANTLY
OVER THE LAST 3 TO 5 WE HAVE
MUCH BETTER QUALITY DIED UP
THE KEYS, MUCH GREATER
CONFIDENCE IN THE ASSUMPTIONS
AND THEY'VE TOLD THE OUTLOOK
AS IT RELATES TO HOW THIS
BUSINESS WILL CONTINUE ON FOLD
THE SECOND, FACT THERE WAS
THAT DOUBT EXPERIENCE WITH
THIS BLOCK HAS BEEN ACTUALLY
VERY GOOD. UGLY LOOK FULL LIST
ON A MONTHLY AND QUARTERLY
BASIS. AND IT'S BEING VERY
CONSISTENT WITH WHAT WE'RE
EXPECTING. AND THEN FINALLY,
PUTTING A LOT OF INTO ORGANIC
ACTIONS TO HELP MANAGE THIS
BUSINESS AS WELL. AS WE CAME,
ONE EXAMPLE OF THAT IS THE USE
OF ADVANCED ANALYTICS AND TO
REALLY IMPROVE DETECTION
CAPABILITIES. I THINK IT'S A
COMBINATION OF THOSE FACT IS
THAT IT REALLY FACILITATED
THIS FIRST TRANSACTION. AND I
THINK IT'S GOING TO BE A
CATALYST TEACHER TRANSACTIONS
AND JUST TO UNDERLINE KIND OF
WHAT WE'RE TALKING ABOUT.
>> WHEN YOUR LIFE ENSURING IT
BECAUSE YOU'RE TALKING ABOUT
DATE IT SO CRUCIAL HERE WHEN
YOUR LIFE INSURER, YOU HAVE
ALL KINDS OF DATA TO ESTIMATE
MORTALITY. LONG-TERM CARE. AS
I UNDERSTAND IT, THE DATA IS A
LITTLE BIT MORE COMPLEX. YOU
DON'T KNOW WHEN SOMEBODY IS
GOING FALL ILL OR YOU DIDN'T
KNOW AS ACCURATELY AS PERHAPS
YOU DO, I ON THE ON THE
MORTALITY SIDE. AM EXPLAINING
THAT CORRECTLY?
>> YOU LEROY. YOU KNOW, WE'RE
IN THE BUSINESS OF TAKING
RISKS AND WE'RE IN THE
BUSINESS OF TAKING LONG-TERM
BETS. AND WE USED TO HELP
SUPPORT THE CONFIDENCE THAT WE
HAVE AROUND HOW THOSE
ASSUMPTIONS WILL UNFOLD. SO
THE MORE DATA THAT WE GET, THE
BETTER, THE ABILITY TO PREDICT
THE OUTLOOK AND THE FUTURE.
AND AGAIN, TO THIS BLOCK OF
BUSINESS. IT'S BEING
HISTORICALLY QUITE YOUNG FROM
A RELATIVE AND NOW WE'VE
REACHED THAT. I THINK IT
TIPPING POINT WITH DIED AND
REALLY SUPPORTS THE QUALITY OF
THE ASSUMPTIONS THAT WE'VE GOT
A AND ALSO SAY THE ONE THING
THAT WHERE WHAT UNIQUE WITH IS
THAT WE IN CANADA UPDATE OUR
ZONING VERY REGULARLY. THAT'S
NOT NECESSARILY THE CASE.
EVERY WORLDS IN OTHER
JURISDICTIONS. AND THEN OUR
REGULATOR ALSO BE REQUIRES
AUSTIN OR ONLY HAVE OUR OWN
VIEW OF WHAT THE ASSUMPTIONS
WILL LOOK LIKE. ALSO REQUIRES
US TO HAVE AN INDEPENDENT PEER
REVIEW OF ASSUMPTIONS. SO THAT
REALLY YOU SPERRY CONFIDENT
THAT ASSUMPTIONS OPERATE.
AGAIN, THIS TRANSACTION HAS
VALIDATED THE PRINCE BECAUSE
WE'VE GOT GOOD PARTY THIS
WILLING TO TRANSACT WITH US.
AND PRETTY MUCH VALIDATED THAT
WHAT WE PREDICT THE FUTURE IS
THE WHITE IN LOOKING AT THE
BUSINESS.
>> DO YOU HAVE A TIMELINE OF
OF WHEN, YOU KNOW, IT SOUNDS
LIKE THERE COULD BE SOMETHING
ELSE TO HAVE A TIMELINE OF OF
ONE ANOTHER DEAL LIKE THIS
COULD BE ANNOUNCED.
>> IT'S HARD PREDICT FUTURE
AND I KNOW WHAT DOES SPECULATE
ON WHEN WE DO TRANSACTIONS.
BUT WE'VE ON A A HUGE JOURNEY
TO TRANSFORM OUR COMPANY, AS I
MENTIONED EARLIER. AND WE
THINK VERY EFFECTIVE. THE LAST
5 AT DOING EXACTLY THAT. IN
LAST FRIDAY'S, WE FREED UP
MORE THAN 10 BILLION DOLLARS
OF CAPITAL. AS A RESULT OF
THAT, WE THINK ARE THE ARE
ONLY ABOUT COMPANY FROM ABOUT
11% TO ALMOST 60% 15.7% Q3 AND
LONG-TERM CARE AND RW A TEASE
HAS GONE REPRESENTING 24% OF
OUR EARNINGS TO WITH THIS
TRANSACTION NOW ONLY
REPRESENTING 11%. SO WE'VE
BEEN VERY ACTIVE IN
ORGANICALLY WITH DIVESTING
THOSE BLOCKS OF BUSINESSES
THAT ARE HIGHER RISK, BUT ALSO
HAVE LOWER ARROW LEANNE
RETURNS AND DEPLOYING THAT
CAPITAL TO HIGHER RETURN
BUSINESSES OR RETURNING IT
BACK TO SHAREHOLDERS BUYBACKS,
WHICH IS OBVIOUSLY A KEY THAT
WE CREATE VALUE TO
SHAREHOLDERS. AND WE THINK
THAT THERE'S FOR US TO DO ON
ON THAT FRONT. AND THEN
CERTAINLY YOU ANNOUNCED IT IN
CONJUNCTION WITH THIS ON THE
ON THE CALL THAT YOU ON
YESTERDAY WITH ANALYSTS, THERE
WERE QUESTIONS ABOUT HOW THIS
AFFECTS YOU. YOU MENTIONED A
RETURN ON EQUITY, YOU'RE
TRYING TO TARGET.
>> A HIGHER NUMBER THERE. HOW
DOES THIS AFFECT SOMETHING
LIKE EARNINGS GROWTH AND
DIVIDEND GROWTH? IS IT ALL
SORT OF DIRECTIONALLY
POSITIVE?
>> IT IS VERY POSITIVE. SO
BECAUSE WITH DEPLOYING WILL
THAT AWAY FREEING UP FROM THIS
TRANSACTION TO WAS BUYBACKS,
IT MEANS THAT THIS TRANSACTION
IS ACCRETIVE TO EARNINGS PER
SHARE AND RETURN ON EQUITY. SO
WE THINK THIS IS A, YOU KNOW,
GREAT, A GREAT OUTCOME AND
IT'S REALLY A FUNCTION OF THE
FACT THAT WE TRY TO DO THIS
BLOCK OF BUSINESSES, WHICH
AGAIN AGGREGATE HAVE A RETURN
ON EQUITY OF ABOUT 10% WHEN
THE TOTAL COMPANY'S RETURN ON
EQUITY IS CLOSER 60%. TRADED
THAT A MULTIPLE OF EARNINGS OF
ABOUT 9.5 TIMES. SO THAT'S
GREAT WAY FOR US TO AGAIN
CREATE VALUE TO SHAREHOLDERS
THROUGH TRANSACTING THESE
BLOCKS, WHICH ARE HIGH RISK
AND LOWER ITS. I FELT IT WAS
IMPORTANT TO KIND OF GET INTO
THE WEEDS ON THIS DEAL.
>> FOR SHAREHOLDERS,
ESPECIALLY LONG-TERM
SHAREHOLDERS IN MANULIFE. I
KIND OF MENTIONED THAT $28 PER
SHARE. ROY ON THE STOCK. IT
HAS BEEN A STUBBORN LIVE,
RIGHT? AND YOU KNOW THAT IT
HASN'T BEEN ABLE TO GO
MEANINGFULLY ABOVE THAT SINCE
THE FINANCIAL CRISIS. AND ARE
YOU THINKING ABOUT THIS? AND
KNOW EXECUTIVES DON'T LIKE TO
OBSESS OVER THE STOCK PRICE,
BUT ARE YOU THINKING ABOUT
THIS IS KIND OF LEAVING A
CHAPTER BEHIND, CREATING A
BASE TO KIND DO DO WELL BY
LONG-TERM SHAREHOLDERS.
>> WELL, I THINK IT YOU HIT
THE NAIL ON THE HEAD, YOU
KNOW, FOCUSES ON CREATING
VALUE TO SHAREHOLDERS OVER THE
LONG TIME AND IT HAS TO BE
SUSTAINABLE. THERE'S REAL
REASON ANY VALUE IN CREATING
ANYTHING THAT WHITE GIVE US A
SCHOLTEN BENEFIT, BUT DRIVING
SUSTAINABLE LONG-TERM VALUE.
AND YES, LONG-TERM CARE HAS
BEING THE BIGGEST DRAG ON AN
AL SHARE VALUATION AND
MULTIPLE. WE DO THINK THIS IS
CATALYST TO CHANGE. WE'RE
QUITE OPTIMISTIC ABOUT THE
VALUE. WE CAN CREATE SOME A
SHARE HOLD A PERSPECTIVE
DIDN'T THESE VERY ATTRACTIVE
AT APPROXIMATELY WE'VE GOT
INCREDIBLY STRONGLY SHOULD
POSITIONS IN NORTH AMERICA.
BUT HERE IN CANADA, N IN THE
U.S. WITH SOME GREAT
BUSINESSES WHERE WHERE LEAD
DRIVING GREAT GROWS AT GREAT
RETURNS AND WE'VE GOT THIS IS
AN GROWTH ENGINES, ALL WEALTH
AND ASSET MANAGEMENT AND ASIA.
SO I I THINK WE'RE A PRETTY
COMPELLING ARGUMENT AND TURNED
WORLD WHERE WE ARE GOING TO
SEE MY TO SLOW GROWTH IN
CERTAIN JOB HAVING THE
DIVERSITY OF THE BUSINESS THAT
SPANS MULTIPLE JOB OR FEES AND
THE LAND OF BUSINESS THAT'S
GOING TO BENEFIT FROM HIGHER
RATE ENVIRONMENT. I THINK WE
PROVIDE A PRETTY COMPELLING
ARGUMENT FOR WHY WE SHOULD BE
AN INVESTMENT CHOICE. ACTION
YET. LET'S TALK ABOUT THAT
HIGHER RATE ENVIRONMENT. IF
YOU'LL PERMIT ME A MACRO
QUESTION. THAT'S KIND OF THE
THE MACRO QUESTION OF THE DAY.
>> THE VIEW THAT WE'RE DONE
WITH RATE HIKES, THE MARKET
PRICING IN RATE CUTS.
>> HOW DO YOU THINK ABOUT THAT
IS SOMEBODY SAYS, YOU KNOW,
WE'RE POSITIONING FOR A HIGHER
RATE ENVIRONMENT
>> YEAH, I THINK ONLY EXPERTS
THAT THE LAST 18 MONTHS IS
CENTRAL BANKS REALLY. I'VE
SEEN INFLATION AND WANTING TO
INFLATION UNDER CONTROL. AND
WITH THAT HAS COME A LOT OF
UNCERTAINTY AND CONCERN. FOLKS
HAVE NOT REALLY HAD A CLEAR
VIEW ON HOW HIGH RATES WILL
NEED TO GO TO CONTAIN
INFLATION AND HOW LONG
INFLATION WILL LEAD TO COME.
HE'S FOR THOSE HIGH RIGHT
START TO KICK GAME ENCOURAGING
IS THAT WE'VE SEEN INFLATION
SLOWING. NOW WE START SEE
ACTUALLY COME DOWN. SO THERE
IS IN LINE YOU THAT WE'RE
GOING TO SEE LESS HIKING
POSSIBLY EVEN A FEW CUTS.
INFLATION IS GOING TO BE A
THING SOUTHERLY STICKIER THAN
IT HAS BEEN IN THE PAST. AND
AS A RESULT, I THINK WE'RE
GOING TO BE IN A REASONABLE
ENVIRONMENT, RIGHT
PERSPECTIVE, THAT RATES WILL
BE HIGHER THAN WHAT WE'VE SEEN
OVER THE LAST DECADE QUITE
HONESTLY, THE LAST DECADE AS
BEING MORE UNUSUAL. THEN WHEN
YOU LOOK BACK. SO RIGHTS WERE
ALL LIES THAT 0 MONEY WAS
FREE. SO THAT WASN'T
NECESSARILY A REALISTIC
SCENARIO. AND I THINK WHAT
WE'RE MOVING TO NOW IS GOING
TO END UP WITH SOMETHING YOU
COULD, WE MIGHT SEE THE SHORT
END OF THE CAUSE COME DOWN A
LITTLE BUT IT WILL BE A HIGHER
RATE ENVIRONMENT I THINK
THAT'S MANAGEABLE